Guide to the Horatio Southgate Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Horatio Southgate papers
1834-1891
MS 77
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
(15 boxes)
Bishop in the Protestant Episcopal Church and missionary. Sermons, writings and correspondence dating from Southgate's years as a missionary in Turkey (1836-1844) and as rector of churches in Boston (1852-1858) and in New York (1859-1872). These papers were formerly called the Berkeley-Southgate Papers.
Southgate, Horatio, 1812-1894
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Horatio Southgate Papers (formerly called the Berkeley-Southgate Papers) were placed in Yale University Library in 1938 on perpetual loan from the Berkeley Divinity School. They were given to the Divinity School by Hutchinson Southgate, the bishop's son, in 1897.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Horatio Southgate Papers consist of six linear feet of sermons, miscellaneous writings, and correspondence. The sermons are arranged and listed only by date (of composition rather than delivery when both are available), but there is a partial listing by subject, title, and date and place of delivery in the Cameron article already cited. The miscellaneous writings consist mainly of translation of Middle Eastern Christian religious texts. The correspondence consists mainly of Cameron's photostats and transcriptions of Southgate letters in other manuscript repositories and in private hands. These letters span his career, 1834 to 1891, but the bulk of them fall in the 1840s and 1850s. Many refer to his mission work in Turkey in the 1840s. The volume of photostats also contains a few of Southgate's printed sermons.
The Horatio Southgate Papers (formerly called the Berkeley-Southgate Papers) were placed in Yale University Library in 1938 on perpetual loan from the Berkeley Divinity School. They were given to the Divinity School by Hutchinson Southgate, the bishop's son, in 1897.
Biographical / Historical
Horatio Southgate, 1812-1894
Southgate, Horatio, P.E. Bishop, b. in Portland, Me., 5 July 1812. He was graduated at Bowdoin in 1832, and then went to the Andover theological seminary, intending to enter the ministry. Two years later he applied for orders in the Episcopal church, and was confirmed in October 1834. He was ordained deacon in Trinity church, Boston, Mass., 12 July 1835, by Bishop Griswold, and soon afterward was appointed by the foreign committee of the board of missions to make an investigation of the state of Mohammedanism in Turkey and Persia. He sailed from New York in April 1836 and was occupied for five years in this field of research. On his returning to the United States he was ordained priest by St. Paul's chapel, New York city, 3 Oct 1839, by Bishop Benjamin T. Onderdonk. He was appointed missionary to Constantinople in 1840 and served for four years in that capacity, during which time he made a tour through Mesopotamia. The Episcopal church having resolved henceforth to send bishops into the foreign missionary field, Dr. Southgate was consecrated bishop for the dominions and depndencies of the sultan of Turkey, in St. Peter's church, Philadelphia, Pa., 26 Oct 1844.
In the following year he returned to Constantinople, and was occupied in the duties of his office until 1849. He then came back to the United States and offered his resignation, which was accepted by the house of bishops in October 1850. He received the degree of S.T.D. From Columbia in 1845 and the same from Trinity in 1846. He was elected bishop of California in 1850 and of Hayti in 1870, but declined. In 1851 he went to Portland, Me. and organized St. Luke's parish, now the cathedral church of the diocese. The following year he accepted the rectorship of the Church of the Avent, Boston, which he held until the close of 1858. In the autumn of 1859 he became rector of Zion church, New York city, and discharged the duties of that post for thirteen years, resigning in September 1872.
Since that date he has lived in retirement in Ravenswood, N.Y. Bishop Southgate's chief publications are Narrative of a Tour through Armenia, Kurdistan, Persia and Mesopotamia (2 vols,, New York, 1840); Narrative of a Visit to the Syrian (Jacobite) Church of Mesopotamia (1844); A Treatise on the Antiquity, Doctrine, Ministry and Worship of the Anglican Church in Green (Constantinople, 1849); Practical Directions for the Observence of Lent (New York, 1850); The War in the East (1855); Parochial Sermons (1859); and The Cross above the Crescent, a Romance of Constantinople (Philadelphia, 1877). He has also contributed freely to church and other literature in magaznies and reviews.
Appleton's Cyclopaedia of American Biography, V, 613-14.
For more information, see Kenneth Walter Cameron, "The Manuscripts of Horatio Southgate...A Discovery," American Church Monthly, XLII (1937), 155-73, a copy of which is in Box 1, Folder 1 of the papers.
Episcopal Church -- Bishops; Episcopal Church -- Missions; Missionaries -- Turkey; Middle East; Turkey -- Religious and ecclesiastical institutions; Sermons; Clergy; Berkeley-Southgate Papers; Southgate, Horatio, 1812-1894
- Inventory
  - Kenneth W. Cameron, "The Manuscripts of Horatio Southgate – A Discovery," American Church Monthly, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Sermons, 1835 October - 1849 December (Box 1)
  - Sermons, 1850 January-1851 July (Box 2)
  - Sermons, 1851 August-1853 February (Box 3)
  - Sermons, 1853 February (cont'd)-1854 September (Box 4)
  - Sermons, 1854 September (cont'd)-1856 December (Box 5)
  - Sermons, 1857 January-1858 March (Box 6)
  - Sermons, 1858 May-1860 December (Box 7)
  - Sermons, 1860 December (cont'd)-1863 January (Box 8)
  - Sermons, 1863 February-1865 June (Box 9)
  - Sermons, 1865 June (cont'd)-1868 March (Box 10)
  - Sermons, 1868 March (cont'd)-1886 April (Box 11)
  - Sermons, undated (Box 12)
  - "Armenian Phrase Book. Dec 8, 1843" (Box 13)
  - "Koray's Preface to Plato's Catechism, Translated from the Greek", undated (Box 13)
  - "Armenian Translation of Portions of [ ? ]'s Festivals and Fasts", undated (Box 13)
  - An unidentified work on Eastern Orthodox theology, translated by Southgate. Also, "Treatise concerning Melchizedek. By the Same Author", undated (Box 13)
  - "A Syriac [ ? ]", undated (Box 14)
    Scope and Contents
    According to a researcher in 2009, this comprises Psalms 1-88 in Turkish, written in Syriac characters.
  - "Chronological List of Coptic Patriarchs. Arabic, with English Translations", undated (Box 14)
  - "Treatise in reply to a Mohammedan Inquirer, by Maximilian, Patriarch of the Greek [ ? ] Church of Egypt", undated (Box 14)
  - "Canons of Clemens, Book of the Apostles, Canons of the Apostles, etc. Arabic, with Table of Contents in English", undated (Box 14)
  - "S. Clemens' Doctrine of the Apostles Concerning Discipline. Arabic", undated (Box 14)
  - "Treatise on the Anglican Church. The Original English", undated (Box 14)
  - "The Communion Service of the American Church. Armenian Translation", undated (Box 14)
  - Letters, Horatio Southgate to Rev. J.J. Robertson, 1841-1845, undated (Box 15)
  - Letter, Charles Ede to Horatio Southgate, 1849 January 11 (Box 15)
  - "A Collection of Letters and Other Memorabilia Concerning the Rt. Rev. Horatio Southgate... Collected by Kenneth Walter Cameron": photostats, transcripts, and printed matter, 1834 - 1891 (Box 15)